coming back to protein and amino acids
for a minute
so amino acids are the building block of
protein they are foundational for making
neurotransmitters are also foundational
for making just structure everywhere
including neural tissue structure as far
as foundations go because we can
supplement right and so like obviously
for for dopamine's and catecholamines is
why we have the the DL PA and the
n-acetyl tyrosine and quality of it but
to just have foundational amino acid
sufficiency what are some key things
people can do well I mean truly
supplementation if you're not taking
complete proteins in the diet and that
and that's that's the key I mean first
and foremost take complete proteins in
the diet I mean you're talking about
proteins that are more complete would be
things like a whey protein concentrate
or a egg protein you can get complete
proteins with vegetable sources but they
usually have to have added pieces to
them so you have to have quite a variety
of vegetables to get all of the
essential amino acids in there because
vegetables are notorious for missing
certain essential pieces but if you mix
it up really well and you've mean it
really takes some good planning as a nun
as an vegetarian or a vegan has to
really plan well with the vegetables
that they take throughout a day so that
they can create that complete mix of
these essential amino acids or they will
be missing certain ones like missing the
nails for the house I mean you know you
can have all this this great material to
build the house but without those nails
you're not going to have a solid solid
structure and they that's what happens
in the body when you're missing one of
those one of those key pieces and you
know tyrosine Tiger seems a big one and
you know there's not really much
toxicity with amino acids I mean you can
have the body will tend to take the
amino acids in through gluconeogenesis
it'll actually create carbohydrates out
of them so it'll just break
down if you have an excess of the amino
acid so you're not really at risk for
getting excess but it's very common to
get deficiencies in the amino acids and
that's why supplementing with with the
amino acids either in a protein powder
or in a supplement that's very directed
at the mix that's required for the brain
like qualia gives you that baseline that
at least keeps you above that that
deficiency threshold so are there any
particular protein that you suggest
people avoid or that they might want to
avoid you know I don't I don't prefer
the soy proteins and I know this isn't
going to gain me any favors in the
vegetarian community but you know i the
the soy proteins so I just it contains
too many things that are potentially
toxic to the body I mean you're talking
about the electing contents you're
talking about the the the serves the the
estrogen receptor modifiers those kind
of things which I've seen some very
negative impacts from those and and you
know the argument goes both ways I mean
you talk about red meat and you talk
about the carcinogens and the toxicities
that are associated with that so it's
always a balancing act between these two
and you know I I kind of fall in that
mid-range where I like the eggs and
seafood as my primary protein sources
they give a pretty complete mix with
those but when you're when you're
dealing with specialty diets that are
not really conducive to the human
physiology they're not ideal for the
human physiology you're gonna have to to
get some of those base nutrients from
somewhere else and you know with when
I'm when I have and I have quite a few
vegetarian clients when I'm with them
though I actually set up their regimen
based on what their primary foods
intakes are so I do end up supplementing
them a little bit more with with the
other end of the spectrum and the Paleo
and add in style eaters I mean I'm
dealing more with mitigating toxicities
and inflammation so you know you don't
have a
it's not like ok well there's a perfect
diet the that is ideal you've got to
balance that between the individual
preferences that people have now for
people who are wanting to kind of dial
it in more and know if a diet they're on
is really working well for them do you
do amino acid testing so you know of
amino acids or something like that to
get a sense of where people's amino acid
profile is you know I used to do those
and just you know the amino acids I mean
unless you're looking at a glaring
deficiency on those tests it's it's not
that helpful I mean you know the meal
you had the night before is really going
to affect what what you're seeing in the
blood is just the test by itself looking
at adequacy it's it was more of just
looking at the history and the the
current lifestyle habits oh man I'd
rather have people document their food
intake for for two weeks then spend the
money on an amino acid test in general I
mean and resorting regarding sufficiency
with with protein for different body
types so how I mean there are obviously
some people who went vegan felt healthy
for a while and then started feeling
like they ran into some challenges other
people felt less healthy right away
other people felt healthy healthier
enduringly so there's obviously genetics
and there's obviously how someone does
it there's also genetics that are
involved and other physiologic factors
that are involved speak to that well the
first first thing I note with most
people they go in the vegetarian diet is
that they generally thrive initially I
mean they're they're all about it I mean
and a lot of it has to do with the
calorie restriction I mean that low
calorie intake is pretty common with a
vegetarian diet and people feel really
good on that they also feel good because
we're getting rid of some toxicities
that they're going to get from the meats
but vegetables have their own sets of
toxins as well what I find is and it
goes back to that triage theory of
micronutrients is it's not a complete
diet I mean
you know we're omnivores by physiology
and we require certain nutrients and and
you can you can do well you can thrive
for a long time on the vegetarian diet
if you're monitoring those
micronutrients and making sure you're
supplementing the risks for deficiencies
but what happens is over time and and it
may take 1012 years of being on the diet
I've seen people that want 15 years
before their health really collapsed but
that triage theory is that background
stuff that's really required for
long-term health and optimal thriving
gets gets put on the back backburner and
just does not not function well so the
overt stuff that you're gonna pay
attention to you're gonna feel that and
you're gonna you're gonna see that but
you're not really paying attention to
that that deep stuff that is all about
long-term thriving and like I said it's
not that you shouldn't do it it's just
more of really paying attention to the
fact that this is going on and making
sure you're doing things to to mitigate
that that potential outcome so just to
clarify wrap up a few things for people
so in a essential amino acid is an amino
acid we have to get from food other
amino acids or ones that our body can
create from the essential amino acids
complete protein contains all the
essential amino acids eight of them but
our body has 23 or so primary amino
acids that are involved some proteins
like eggs have kind of all 23 or most of
them because it's everything necessary
to make a little creature right and so
it has a particularly easy time
providing all the amino acids if the
body's having a hard time converting
them for other deficiency reasons which
is why some people do particularly well
with those like beyond complete proteins
most plants they all have amino acids
but they don't necessarily have all
eight essential amino acids most of the
time they don't so if you get a wide
variety of different legumes beans nuts
seeds greens you're gonna get different
amino acid profiles from each so where
people are getting amino acids from food
pretty wide variety is relevant the few
plant source
of complete proteins if you're not
taking extracts like a brown rice
protein which represents 1 or 2 percent
of the total brown rice the allergies
are a particularly unique source I think
is worth mentioning if people do
spirulina chlorella blue-green algae
they're just kind of micronutrient dense
across so many categories detox and yes
they have much more than that even I
mean that those are awesome yeah it's
just supplement so I do know a lot of
people who are doing kind of vegetarian
vegan super food oriented diets algie's
bee pollen things that are very nutrient
dense and amino acid dense are something
they oftentimes supplement as a food
source with if someone wants to learn
more about protein and amino acids and
getting enough amino acids on a
plant-based diet I'll just recommend
real quick I think there's a website
called vegan bodybuilding comm that has
a lot of good resources and a lot of
athletes you know have kind of really
dialed that in to watch the full episode
or to subscribe to the podcast click the
link in the description or visit us at
neuro hacker.com slash collective
insights
[Music]